[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software flavio junkie era thanks
for coming on software engineering radio
yeah sure nice talk to you Jeff thanks
for inviting me yeah so today we're
gonna be talking about Apache zookeeper
and I guess some you know you can call
it distributed coordination so why don't
we start off by talking about what is
the purpose of Apache zookeeper what
problems does it try to solve this is
this is a very interesting question
because zookeepers related to what I
would say meta operations of a cluster
so you have a disability patient it has
a number of servers running your
application and there are a number of
operations that you have to do that
they're not necessarily related to the
application directly but you need you
need to do them together your cluster
going for example you might need to
elect a master among the group of
servers and the end user it's not gonna
is not gonna know that there is a master
but you know it's for your application
to run correctly you need to elect that
master and so zookeeper helps you with
that those kinds of tasks and when I say
animation clusters you can think of
clusters are pretty large clusters say
hundreds or thousands of servers trying
to do this kind of of coordination and
although I use master election as an
example there are many of these tasks
that are sort of common when you're
trying to implement a distributed
application you can think of things like
group membership you want to know which
members of your cluster actually up
right so if you have hundreds of of
servers running it might be the case
that a small fraction of those are not
up at a given time you'd like to know
who they are so that you can make
assignments accordingly a pretty common
use of zookeepers also metadata manage
and so you need to store some metadata
reliably you need that metadata to be
distributed across the cluster in a
consistent manner and so zookeeper helps
you with with all that and so there's
this there's a an Airbnb Tech Talk that
I watched about zookeeper and features
Patrick hunt and I'll uh put it in the
show notes but so he talks about
zookeeper and he frames his discussion
in terms of fallacies about distributed
computing and these sorts of fallacies
that he listed were like you know you
have a reliable network there is zero
latency infinite bandwidth you have no
problems with security there's no
changing network topology and all these
things are not actually true in in your
typical distributed system there's some
kind of problem that violates one of the
fallacies that I just mentioned
so is it reasonable to look at zookeeper
as a patch for these fallacies like a
sort of way of sort of eliminating them
so you don't have to think about them as
much do we look at those fallacies is
what developers end up doing in their
code when they try to implement the
tasks I was automation before in a quick
and dirty manner right so it's not that
people actually make those assumptions
that the network is reliable there is
little eight and so on but but if it's
not your main goal right to implement
those tasks if your task is to implement
I don't know a crawler or or a datastore
or something odds are that you you try
to do this tasks like master election
group membership and so on in a quick
and dirty manner and so you end up
simplifying your code and ends having
the problems that those fallacies are
actually alluding to I prefer to look at
zookeeper not as a patch for those
things but more of a structured and
natural way to look at the problem so it
gives a way to developers to reason
about these problems in a much more
natural way which leads to more robust
implementations so looks like kind of
think about I want I kind of want to
discuss it from from the point of view
of the of a typical user so for example
like let's say I'm a user
that has designed some application that
is like you said that treats these
issues these policies as just
non-existent and and I you know let's
say I built the way that I built my
application was quick and dirty and I
wasn't really considering the fallacies
so how am I going to start using
zookeeper to solve these problems you
know I have this cat this collection of
distributed systems problems and I want
to sort of collect all of them in a
single context or look at them through a
single lens and I guess that lens would
be zookeeper so how do I start using
zookeeper to manage those issues across
my application there are two points for
for beginners I would say one is to look
at the the API the API is actually very
simple the core API is very simple has
six calls it allows you to actually
manipulate the small files of Lacaze
nodes you know you create them you can
you can read them you can change their
data and once you're familiar with the
API which shouldn't take very long it's
again only six calls it's good to go and
look at recipes so recipes are this way
these ways of using the API to implement
the various tasks that that people care
about you know so synchronization
primitives like locks if you're trying
to do master election that has been a
number of implementations out there of
master election on top of on top of
zookeeper and so I think that this is a
pretty good way of going about it so I'm
sending the API or at least have a
cursory understanding of the API and
then go learn from from the recipes so
it's just a lot of experience out there
so let's say for example like I'm
developing a game and the games has shot
up in popularity and I wasn't prepared
to scale and I'm starting to scale now
and so it becomes this huge distributed
problem and I realized I want to use
zookeeper because I've heard of it as a
solution so could you maybe outline what
a recipe would look like or what am I
going to start so I have you know Z
nodes and zookeeper you know what am I
going to start to be doing with those Z
nodes yeah so
you can for example have metadata of a
user stores ooh keeper or in fact for
all your users you can have say one xeno
containing their metadata and the
metadata could be the profile of the
user plus the scores of of the user or
the status of the user for a given game
in a well level the user is at some
point or how many points it has scored
optional so that could be a way of doing
this other things and to be very honest
I have never tried to apply zookeeper
directly to your game so I'm coming up
with this on the fly you could you could
think of assigning one server to to
handle when starting your application
not a zookeeper server right so one of
your application servers to handle the
traffic of a given user so that could be
the master for that user right and and
you know if you want to make your game
fall torrent if the master for that user
crashes you don't want your your user to
be to be offline as a consequence of
that crash right so you you want to go
and allocate another another server to
deal with with that user and that's
where the the fault or and a master
election that zookeeper provides kicks
in and so instead you know just to get
into a specific question when you're
putting data in these various nodes and
these nodes have to be consistent with
one another how is the data being
propagated from Z node to Z node maybe
this is a question that would be more
appropriate for later in the
conversation but I mean is it is it sort
of like a like a gossip type protocol or
how how exactly does that work no it's
it's um let me start by saying that in a
zookeeper ensemble so ensemble's is the
name we give to the group of servers
that uh that is serving a given
zookeeper instance so when you connect
you know you're a client of zookeeper
right so you have an application that
that binds to the to the client library
and and it connects to an instance of
zookeeper that instance is well it could
be a standalone but typically for
production you use they have a wrap
study and so that set of replicas record
an ensemble so each of the servers in
the Indian ensemble contains a full copy
of all the Z notes that have been stored
in that instance of of zookeeper so what
we do is whenever you come and say
create the Z node what the service is
going to do is it's going to propose
that we create you know that don't
stumble create stands you know and in
the case that there is agreement on the
creation of that C node then all servers
are going to record it and so all
servers in a zookeeper ensemble will
contain a copy of that C node now the
specific protocol we use is now gossiped
we use what we call an atomic broadcast
protocol so it provides stronger
guarantees so guarantees that are all
the updates that apply to those replicas
they come in the same order it does not
guarantee though that they come at the
same time right so we do not go and see
that they come at the same time we only
guarantee that they come in in the same
order and so all those replicas are
gonna apply those state updates in state
updates being as you know being created
as not being deleted the data obviously
not being changed you know so those are
all state updates and so and so with
this protocol all those setup dates are
gonna are gonna be fed to all those
servers in the same order sure okay and
so I guess you know zooming out a little
and going back to the high level let's
talk a bit about what is and what isn't
the zookeeper so like I'm trying to like
sort of go back and forth between
perspectives of people who are a little
more familiar with distributed systems
and may be familiar with zookeeper and
then people who are less familiar with
it and so so maybe for the people who
are less familiar maybe we could put a
little more of a definition on what is
and what isn't zookeeper like is it a
database is it a file system is it a key
value store
how should a developer who comes into a
new company and sees okay we've got this
zookeeper thing running what like what
am I supposed to think about this thing
so that's why we sort of coined
this term coordination service because
it shares properties with all the
systems you mentioned my bio systems are
key value stores databases even but but
it's none of that
it's again it shares share similarities
but it doesn't I don't think we can we
can say that zoo keepers any of those so
for example if I think of key value
stores updates you know so you can think
of Z nodes in zookeeper as as you note
has a path as I can you can look at that
as a key and the day of the signal can
be seen as as the value of a for that
key but it's if you look at any store
you don't try to order updates across
keys or you don't even try to organize
to provide a hierarchical organization
as we do with with C nodes and this
hierarchy turns out to be e to be
important because one of the calls that
we have is is cat children right so you
get the children of a z node inside
their hierarchy and that turns out to be
very important many of the recipes that
that we have decide in the end it shares
properties with all those those classes
of systems but I think it really
deserves a you know a name of its own or
a class of its own so a distributed
coordination system is what is what you
would call it exactly and in the case of
zookeeper we also we also call it a
coordination kernel because in reality
zookeeper does not expose any of the
primitives themselves it doesn't you
know so if you look at the API you're
not gonna see anything about master
election you're not gonna say anything
about locks it's not gonna see anything
about group membership all right it's
it's about what you can build on top of
it
right so the recipes are very important
part of zookeeper but zookeeper itself
only provides the kernel that allows you
to implement all that so because those
things are less exposed things like
leader election does that make it like
once you start to let's say you start to
scale a system with zookeeper and maybe
you want to loosen certain requirements
or or tighten certain requirements are
there other things that are sort of kept
from the user because of the simple API
that make it may be more difficult to
fine-tune or or or perhaps the scale or
is or is that not really an issue I
think it's actually the other way around
I think the fact that we have an API
that does not expose any of those
primitives directly gives the the
developer more flexibility one good
example is is master election there are
at least two different ways of
implementing master election that has
been using in across applications right
so if we were each implements my
selection in a given way that would be a
single way of doing it right and because
we have this core API that you can you
can build your recipes with you can
think of different ways of terenia of
doing these tasks
now with respect to scalability the
scare bidding imitations of zookeeper
are actually related to the core
protocol which is fairly fundamental and
I believe any system that implements
this kind of coordination would have the
same limitations but with respect to the
to the API I think what we did in
zookeepers is actually a great thing
because it gives flexibility into the
implementation of of primitives okay I
understand so you're saying that that
the the things that you do need to
access in maybe the underlying API
maybe but beneath the API layer they
essentially are accessible but it's just
you have to get to them through the API
yes okay so let's talk about some
specific use cases what are some ways
that you have seen zookeeper deployed so
when you refer to use cases I can think
of of the actual recipes that people
have used like well the examples I can
think of with respect to recipes are
master election which is pretty popular
group membership metadata management and
a lot of the synchronization primitives
I don't know like locks or or or
barriers or if you're just if you're
just trying to do conditional updates
right so you have multiple clients
trying to updates the same Z node and
you want to make sure that it doesn't
nodes
this is nodes update in a consistent
manner this is fairly abstract right so
I'm just giving you some tasks in the
recipe set up that people have
implemented now if I go on one level up
and think about the actual applications
that have uses two applications that are
fairly popular and come to mind are data
stores like age based and in Hadoop in
both HDFS and in yarn a zookeeper has
been used for high availability so for
example for master election and for rely
for reliable store so ok could you could
you maybe provide like higher level I
mean I I definitely understand what
you're saying but maybe you could
provide a mapping from some recipe
- maybe like business side use cases
sure so let's let's pick
let's pick Master election okay so let's
say that uh um you have a master for
your file system like the name node in
HDFS right let's say you want to elect a
leader
the simplest way of electing a leader is
to establish a path for for a master
lock all right let's call you a master
lock so you go to zookeeper and say
create slash master lock it doesn't have
to have any data at this point right
great slash master lock and you could
have many clients actually trying to do
this right because zookeeper again
replicates right this rights and all the
replicas see this update in the same
order only one of those clients will be
able to create the Z node right so one
is gonna succeed in creating that Z node
right and the one that gets okay becomes
the master and so he holds the master
lock at that point all the other ones
will won't be able to create they will
get an error message than you know this
is this is in order it exists and and at
that point they know that are they are
not the leader they're not the Masters
and so they have to to follow the master
or watch the master in the case the
master goes away but then the creation
of this you know this is not enough Chua
to make your a your master election
fault-tolerant right the other thing you
want to do is you you want to create
that Z node which with the ephemeral
flag the ephemeral flag is a very is a
very very interesting feature of
zookeeper because it allows that C node
to be deleted indicates the clients the
kinda coin goes away so say the client
crashes the zookeeper is going to
determine that because the session of
that clients can expire and it's gonna
automatically delete the Z node
so all the other clients that were
interested in becoming masters they will
be watching that's you know and when
it's deleted they will know that he has
been deleted and so they will run
another round of master election
right so I have to know that with a
single Z node and the features I have
here's again is one API which is to
create the cenote I created as you know
there's an ephemeral Z node and the
other clients there are not masters they
use the gap data Z node to watch the
master lock and they get a notification
back when the master lock is deleted
that's one example of a task that it can
implement with zookeeper and slowly
popular and you can easily map that you
are you know to use cases like the one I
mention you have the head of a file
system or of a datastore like HBase you
need to make that fall torrent okay that
makes it now that would be relevant on a
you know distributed database type of
system I guess you know whether you're
Facebook that's you know making a
database of billions of people or some
online store that's making a database of
all kinds of products and you need to
keep the things consistent you know the
you know you want one user to be seeing
the same sorts of stuff that another
user is seeing that would that was sort
of what I meant by the higher level
business case but I understand the
mapping so how big of a cluster do you
typically see zookeeper deployed across
how am i scale in my zookeeper cluster
from ten users to a thousand users to a
million to a billion how does that look
I have seen clusters with with thousands
of of clients talking to the same
zookeeper ensemble ensembles of of say
five to seven servers the limitation
there is mostly the amount of traffic
you want impose on on on zookeeper
but the short answer is that so you can
you can have classes of hundreds to
thousands of clients connecting to a
zookeeper in Samba of say five to a to
seven zookeeper servers it's a pretty
typical case and it is is it accurate to
say that zookeeper is strong for systems
with lots of reads and fewer rights
yes yes indeed so right as I explained
before rights required to run this this
atomic broadcast protocol which is
essentially your riding that state
update to all replicas in fact we just
need to wait for a quorum to respond by
we we do we do send the right chewy
chewy everyone but the reads are served
locally right so if I if I had more
servers to up to my ensemble then I can
definitely increase my read capacity not
my write capacity though so it's it's a
system that is is highly targeted to to
read dominated workloads although it
does it does pretty well on on on writes
as well when we we can easily get these
days 20,000 writes per second with with
with implementation we have so it's not
that the volume of of rights has to be
small it's just that we cannot really
scale it at this point so if you go if
you want to go from 20,000 to say
100,000 and eventually Charmeleon then
and there's no way looking for today
actually do this but for the reads it
can increase as much as you want so how
we give a problem is this like have
there been users that have said like oh
we actually can't use zookeeper because
it doesn't want us write aggressively
enough or do people end up using an
alternative service if they if they need
some amount of writes like that they
usually think is that most cases I have
seen where people were requesting
exactly what it said you know so I want
to be able to scale write workloads the
zookeeper was actually not a good fit
for that so a good you know at a high
level good use case for zookeeper is one
in which the rights to zookeeper are
nodding the critical path of your
application so if everything that comes
through your system every change that
comes through your systems we think -
zookeeper that's probably not the right
thing to do you probably need some sort
of biggest or some key value store Chua
to handle that kind of workload
zookeepers reading for the matter
operations I was I was saying before I
was mentioning before and so those
operations they so often what happens is
you have one right to say some metadata
element right so let's say that you have
some
the data that I York listen needs to
know right so you update that metadata
you know date the value of those of
those variables and by updating some Z
node right but you expect all the
servers in your closet to read it so
that translates into one right and and
say thousands of reads right right so
this is a fairly common use case for for
zookeeper sure okay so let's look at a
little bit of history of zookeeper
so zookeeper began at Yahoo and
eventually was moved to Apache as part
of the Hadoop project so I'd like to
talk a bit about why zookeeper was so
important to haddou
that's that's a very interesting
question in fact it was it wasn't
important to Hadoop at a time I think we
ended up as a sub-project of Hadoop
because the Hadoop community was was in
general supportive of the project and
there was also this perception that I
know HDFS and zookeeper were supposed to
have a similar relationship to GFS and
chubby but zookeeper at the time was not
was not used by Hadoop at all okay so
but eventually it's become an important
part of the Hadoop correct yeah but only
after after we left it after I became a
top level project sometime later it was
they started using it for for me no they
che and today you have yarn as well
relying a zookeeper okay could you maybe
give some color on the integration of
that like how is ooh keeper the best
solution for that purpose of hadoo so if
it's the use case as I mentioned before
some a selection storing metadata
reliably these are the things that are
that they are looking for in the in
design those use cases and so zookeeper
is is in that ecosystem it's a very
stable project you know it's battle
tested so it's a it's definitely good a
good element good component you are
chipping that role okay that makes sense
let's let's drill down a little bit into
the different roles in a zookeeper
implementation so you have the roles of
followers leaders well a a leader at
least clients and observers so let's
talk about the the abilities and the
responsibilities or the roles should let
me start with clients so clients connect
to a single server at a time right so
even if you have many other at multiple
replicas even have replicas of the
system the clients going to connect to a
single server at a time so out of those
servers one is the leader as I mentioned
and the others could be followers or
observers they'll leave their processes
or requests I change the state so if if
a client submits a you know say a create
C node that's going to go to the leader
the leaders gonna
produce a transaction which is a state
update it's gonna propose that you are
the followers the followers are gonna
persist that on disk they're gonna
acknowledge you the leader and then the
leaders ready to come in followers are
different from observers so observers do
not vote in that process I just
mentioned observers they just learn the
state changes right the the same changes
have been committed and by doing that
with the main thing you achieve is that
we can increase read capacity without
actually increasing the work the servers
have to do for for a given state change
what I was gonna say so going back to
the leader proposing state change when
you see the response from a majority
that is ready to ID to respond to the
clients and at that point the client
receives it receives a response back and
that's more or less how the flow works
of of requesting zookeeper okay yeah
sure so that makes sense so is there a
specific algorithm that the consensus
protocol or zookeeper is based on like
is it is it sort of like a Paxos type of
consensus or is it maybe like based on
wrath or is there not a close
relationship between the way that
zookeeper maintains consensus and the
way that these things are outlined in
academic papers right so the protocol we
use is called Zab which stands for
zookeeper atomic broadcast it has
elements that are that differ from from
paksas although you can move through
this exercise of mapping pack system how
to choose AB but I read that you paper
suit you notice that there are
differences and the difference is mainly
because of the way we have structured
the the components of the service
leaders and followers by propagating the
state updates and we having this
dependence between the the sequence of
between state changes in the same in the
same sequence which sort of forces to to
stop the consensus protocol during a
leader change so that we could guarantee
that the consistency of this
so it's it is a protocol that is against
that's called sab it's it has many
elements in common with with raft raft
actually came a few years later and
Indian yeah that's the protocol we used
but again both raft and sab have
elements of earlier protocols like axes
I'm sorry could you repeat again with
the differentiating requirement that
incentivize you to make your own
protocol we have this need of when we do
a leader change we need to have
agreements on the initial states of the
new epoch okay so the protocol is
structured in epics right so have either
a leader comes I proposes a bunch of
things a bunch of state changes those
are committed and at some point they'll
either goes away he crashed or it got
suspected of crashing and the new leader
comes so when that new leader comes
before it can start proposing new state
changes it needs to agree with the other
with the other servers what the initial
state of the new epoch is and so that
required us to come up with with a
different with a different protocol okay
yeah I understand so I know that
implementing anything in a distributed
system is can be hard or implementing a
distributed system can be hard
specifically so how did you perform
validation and testing on zookeeper and
how did you achieve a level of
confidence in the correct behavior
because you know anytime you're trying
to implement a distributed feature of
something if you want to test it there's
always sort of the question of if I test
this on three servers is that equivalent
to how it operates on five servers is
that equivalent to operate it to how it
operates on ten servers and so on so how
did you do this validation and testing
it's a combination of reasoning and in
writing Realtors so we did a lot of
reasoning about not only the code but
but the protocols behind it and we have
a lot of tests so in a patch in general
we you ought on generalize so much but
in some people we use we use extensively
j-unit us to test cases that I could be
problematic or they have been
problematic in the past and any time a
change goes in its checked then we have
to run those tests to make sure that
it's not you know there is no violating
or it's not breaking anything there are
that's alright in there and there is
also the test of time right it has been
you know has been running production a
number of places for a long time is this
is not to say that there is no bug right
or that has never been bugs quite the
other way around
I always find these small things that
are that we can fix and that's part of
the work of the community to fix this
this this bug that we find every now and
then but in general I would say that the
customers of zookeeper are really happy
with it over the years I have heard lots
of good comments about it's the
beginning of zookeeper and how he runs
and and so on are there any known edge
cases that result in failure
each case is the result in failure so
could you be a bit more specific about
failure I guess I was unspecific on
purpose because I wanted to see if that
evoked any any is there anything that
you know happens frequently maybe
because it could be just because people
tend to implement something in an
erroneous way and it leads to a
vulnerability at an edge case or maybe
it's something that is inherent and
zookeeper that that leads to an edge
case I'm just curious as to what or you
know how you would define failures and
in the edge cases that would result in
those rights well I guess I can see
failures ending in two ways one is for
example if we ignore the notifications
that zookeeper sense up to the
application right so one example is if
you implement a master election oh let
me actually start back and talk about
sessions a bit so when a client starts
talking to them somebody has to
establish a session right a session can
live through multiple connections so
initially the client connects to a
server but later on that line may move
that session to a different server right
connects disconnects from the first
server connects to a new server but the
session still is still the same if
you're implementing master election what
we strongly recommend is data if you
disconnect from a server right and you
receive that notification from from the
client library the master should stop
doing any kind of master work because at
that point it doesn't know what what the
state of the cluster is it might be the
case that each session has expired right
or it's going to expire soon and in that
case it could become you notes its
decisions or its steps might be
conflicting with with the steps of of
the new master writing this is something
that is problematic so the bottom line
is ignoring look ignoring the other
notifications at the client library
sends up it's a bad idea and doing that
could lead to I to say bad cases in your
application there are failures on on say
the operational
zoo keeper so zoo keeper today's is
sensitive to our to losing disk state it
heavily depends on servers and not
losing disk state to guarantee the
consistency of the data this is not to
say that there is no way around it so if
a server loses it it's this state then
you need to remove that server from the
ensemble in reinserted to guarantee that
there is no consistent consistency
problem this is this is an argument a
sort of a deeper argument into into the
protocol but at a high level this is
business this is what happens
and so if I'm a user that's implemented
my zookeeper system do people typically
do fuzz testing or you know like is
there is there a barrage of random and
unusual events that you can just impose
on the system
as a means of testing it so as I
mentioned we run J Unitas right and that
we are continuously running it and every
time we check in that we also need to
run it before it's checked and users
also keeper tend to have their own set
especially the big the big customers
also keeper they tend to have their own
set of tasks at some point we talked
about fault injection this is not
presenting in zookeeper today so I think
the short answer to your question is
that we don't have anything like like
your suggestion although we have various
test cases and test suits that are that
the various customers run on zookeeper
distributions okay I want to talk about
the cap theorem what is your definition
of cap and do you actually find it
useful do you follow it as a design
principle and could you elaborate on
consistency availability and partition
tolerance right
so the cap work is is be walk a bit old
by now and in the past few years a few
people have actually criticized it
trying to uncover some of the dangers
I'll be using the the cap definitions
loosely oh my hands outside the cap has
always confused me a bit mainly because
it defines terminology in the way that
is that very different from the way I
typically use
so if I think if I think about zookeeper
I would actually say that is it's
consistent it's payable and it's
partitioned arm it's consistent because
it realized in this atomic broadcast
primitive
Sarah you know the set up dates are Toa
order and delivered in order to the
server replicas it's available because a
single crash or a minority
the server replicas being unavailable is
not going to cause the whole system to
be to be unavailable so their baby is is
about the the total amount of time that
the service as a whole is up and finally
it's partition tolerance because it does
not admit split brain so split brain is
a situation in which two or more parts
of the system end up making progress
independently which causes the the state
in which of those parts to diverge one
one compared to the others which is
clearly bad at least in the case of of
zookeeper now
if going back to the cap should that to
the cab work gap as many people expose
is essentially says that we have this
three-part properties and when our
beauty and disability system we need we
picked you so CP CA or AP
I would say that's he doesn't make a lot
of sense
because CA essentially seems that that
partitions do not occur well I'm not
sure how one can control whether
partitions of korah not I think the best
one could do is to is to assume that
that partitions won't occur in the case
they occur you just suffer the
consequences but but but I'm not sure
how much one one has to gain by by just
doing this doesn't sound like a great
way of thinking about systems the
zookeeper fall cleanly into any of the
models provided by cap CP CA or ap be
strict about the cap definitions
zookeeper is really none of those so the
word code isn't necessarily linearizable
because the the regular reads are the
basic reads we have they did not make
the workload really linearizable so it's
not consistent and it doesn't accept
split brain it doesn't admit split brain
so it's not available either
but corn based systems replicated stick
machines which is
an instance of typically fall into the
category of of CP consistent partition
toners so that's really the closest
because it's too soupy per how useful is
cap when it comes to trying to reason
about systems one of the great benefits
of cap is that it provides a common
terminology for people to talk about
their systems but I really think that is
great
I'm just started conversations you know
saw your CP person are your EP person
but thinking deeply about systems in its
relationship cap seems a bit pointless
to me now
I think the cap work is very relevant so
if you read that the cap proof be kept
there improve it's very interesting he
provides it provides a lot of insight
but it's intriguing narrow result
although people keep you know keep you
using it you know in a very broad manner
just to give an example so if I think if
I think about consistency if I pick the
definitions in the in the disability
systems by Andy Tannenbaum so over there
there are there are over ten definitions
of consistency
so narrowing it down to just linearize
ability doesn't sound very wise to me
although granted that linear is a big is
a very important property or from any of
the systems that we build and use would
it make sense to extend the cap theorem
to try to define more finer grained
classifications for systems because
these three dimensions see a and P
consistency availability and partition
tolerance they don't seem to capture the
richness of systems these days I mean
maybe they they do they do provide a
framework in which you can write a proof
but maybe that's not as useful as having
a more rich terminology yes as I said I
think one of the interesting and nice
things of the cap work is that he has
as a chief to create a common simple
terminology that developers of
disabilities systems have have been used
have been using to discuss discuss our
projects I don't think everyone doing
this other assistance bouya understands
the implications of the cab definitions
though
and so if we you are to come up with
something different
I think this this new thing should have
you should make a bit a bit more clear
what's what consistency of the ability
in partition Donna so whatever other
terms will come up with our so that's so
that developers of disability systems
builders do not end up using this term
loosely and misinterpreting what's
actually going on just by using by using
terminology losing but the same time add
as I mentioned I I don't think such such
a small term not a small narrow
terminology or such a concise model it's
great for something else other than just
starting a conversation I really think
that
systems are just so many subtleties and
one says do the things we do that you
need you need to go deeper to understand
what what needs to be done what kind of
properties you're looking at you're
looking for and so on as I was making
this reference to at your consistency
properties there are many consistency
properties one could think of when when
implementing a system and so just
thinking about one or maybe two that
doesn't sound that doesn't sound great
so so a terminology that allows us to to
to convey in a concise manner but in a
precise manner as well what we're trying
to do in a project that wouldn't be a
bad idea but again keeping in mind that
that's but down the road we need to talk
in more detail about things so that we
can we can think more deeply about what
are we trying to achieve
so how does how does zookeeper guarantee
that clients will never detect old data
the zookeeper actually doesn't make that
promise
what zookeeper tries to do is actually
to avoid discussions about time
altogether
so the replica is guaranteed that state
changes come in the same order
also guarantees our replicas receive the
state changes in the same order but he
doesn't mean a guarantee that a client
is going to be some older data right so
it could happen in in a system that you
know that at some point in time two
kinds read different values for the same
C note but over time right declined that
the Reds the the the the older data
eventually we'll be able to see that a
death state update right the newer
version of the data so zookeeper
guarantees the order of updates but not
when they're gonna happen right and so
zookeeper keeps watch over something
that sort of looks like a file system
and in some sense and I'm curious are
are the observers costly like or is the
the notion of being of observing this
file system is it costly like are you
are you just constantly polling and
spending energy and this question may
lend itself to you know maybe I have a
still have kind of a loose understanding
of how a zookeeper works but maybe you
could address that question sure
so when a client sets of watch an Una's
II know but I say I want to receive a
notification when something happens to
this Judah's II know and so their
request goes to zookeeper and to the
servers and the server that receives a
request
annotates their particular path for
their watch and so when he receives the
updates it triggers the notification to
the client so the client has to do no
work on their watch right while it's
connected to a to that server and and
when this state change it is linkage
comes in it the server will produce the
notification and ship it to the to the
client
the burden is mostly on the one server
on the server side okay how horizontally
scalable is zookeeper if I'm growing how
how rapidly can I can I just like can I
just like throw new servers on on
zookeeper and you know say hey rebalance
this or is it more of a complicated
difficult process if you're trying to
scale rights or the amount of state of
zookeeper ensemble then we don't have
any good mechanisms for doing this today
the what you can scale horizontally
scale in zookeeper today is read
capacity right as I was mentioned you
can throw in more more observers or just
increasing number of followers and that
will increase your your your a bit of
doing reads right you can do more reads
for per second okay makes sense so I
guess we can start to close off I'm
curious about where zookeeper is going
so so like what look what is the future
are there are there features that need
to be implemented are there changes that
need to be made or that are going to be
made new features being added the main
feature we have been working on recently
is reconfiguration this is it has been
made recently available in the
three-five branch which was released in
August if I'm if I'm not mistaken but
that's what that branch is not stable
yet and so the community has been
focusing a lot on that on that feature
okay for somebody that's that's getting
started on zookeeper what would you say
are are the best resources to to
consider I know you've mentioned the
recipes several times and certainly you
know we'll link to some of those and and
how to pursue them but what what are
some order some other resources that
people should look at and may and maybe
other other projects that people should
look at right so the Apache curator
project this is definitely a very good
source of not only information but you
can actually use the recipes that they
have implemented so Apache curator the
proposal curator
is to implement the best practices known
of a four zookeeper and so you can learn
a lot by just looking at the recipes and
and you can even be a bit lazy and just
and just use them directly and so it's
definitely a good a good source of
recipes right and knowledge about about
how to program against zookeeper great
and and how can people find out more
about you or follow you on social media
oh yeah so I have a Twitter account it's
FB zoom cater so that's that's my hand
on on Twitter
I'm also in LinkedIn so if you search me
for my name you probably find it and so
that those are our good a a good ways of
following me and I also strongly
encourage the ones interested in in in
zookeeper or learning about zookeeper
contributing to zookeeper to sign up for
for the list for the deathless in the
user list we are always interested in
you know onboarding and new contributors
new commuters and growing the community
so you know I would be happy to see more
people signing up alright talking chants
in Apache okay well that's great
Flavio I want to thank you for coming on
software engineering radio thanks for
inviting me thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radio um to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on iTunes mention a message us on
Twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team at se - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you